Guide to the Walter Albert Stanbury Papers, 1915-1954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Walter Albert Stanbury papers 1915-1954
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Stanbury, Walter Albert.
12.4 Linear Feet 2,676 Items
Methodist clergyman of Ashboro (Randolph County), North Carolina.
Correspondence, articles, sermons, addresses, and other papers relating to Stanbury's (d. 1854) religious activities in North Carolina; together with reports, minutes, and correspondence of the Wesley Foundation, a Methodist student organization, in various North Carolina colleges and universities.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Walter Albert Stanbury Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1948 and 1956.
Biographical Note
Methodist clergyman of Ashboro (Randolph County), North Carolina.
Collection Overview
These papers consist of 2015 sermons delivered by the Reverend Stanbury between 1915 and his death in 1954; addresses; articles; general correspondence; reports, minutes, correspondence, etc. concerning the work of the Wesley Foundation, a Methodist student organization, in N.C. colleges and universities; constitution and minutes of the N.C. Council of Churches, 1935-1937; Homecoming Day address by the Rev. Stanbury at Greensboro College and a copy of the program, March 9, 1940; outlines for conferences on parental education, 1925-1934; correspondence relative to Centenary Methodist Church of Winston-Salem, 1941-1943; folder of correspondence with Irene Price, artist, about a portrait of Furnifold M. Simmons.
In the general correspondence there are letters in 1945 about the appointment of Prof. James T. Cleland to teach homiletics in the Duke Divinity School. The folder labeled "Special Addresses" contains an address the Reverend Stanbury delivered at the funeral of Henry R. Dwire at Winston-Salem in 1944.
There is a scrapbook of newspaper accounts of the Sunday morning service at West Market St. Methodist Episcopal Church, Greensboro, N.C., covering Stanbury's pastorate, 1933-1937.
At some point in his life the Reverend Walter Albert Stanbury changed his middle name from Adair to Albert. His wedding invitation (1909) and his listing in the annuals of Trinity College use "Adair." However, his obituary in the 1954 minutes of the Western North Carolina Conference, his published book, Who's Who in America, and his son Walter Albert Stanbury, Jr., (who wrote both a thesis and a dissertation at Duke University) all use "Albert."
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Wesley Foundation
College students -- Religious life
Methodist Church -- Clergy
Methodist Church -- North Carolina
Methodist Church -- Sermons
Universities and colleges -- North Carolina
Universities and colleges -- Religion
North Carolina -- Religion
Description of Collection
- Walter Albert Stanbury Papers, 1915-1954, (31 boxes)
  The bulk of this collection is sermons given by Walter Albert Stanbury over the course of his career. Some boxes in the collection are out of sequential order from the whole.
  - Information Folder (Box 1)
  - Addresses
  - Articles
  - Correspondence
  - Addresses (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
  - Scrapbook
  - Sermons 1-37
  - Sermons, 38-124 (Box 3)
  - Sermons, 125-216 (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 217-289 (Box 5)
  - Sermons, 290-365 (Box 6)
  - Sermons, 366-459 (Box 7)
  - Sermons, 460-567 (Box 8)
  - Sermons, 568-644 (Box 9)
  - Sermons, 645-725 (Box 10)
  - Sermons, 804-870 (Box 11)
  - Sermons, 726-803 (Box 12)
  - Sermons, 937-1010 (Box 13)
  - Sermons, 871-936 (Box 14)
  - Sermons, 1011-1083 (Box 15)
  - Sermons, 1145-1202 (Box 16)
  - Sermons, 1084-1144 (Box 17)
  - Sermons, 1203-1266 (Box 18)
  - Sermons, 1267-1321 (Box 19)
  - Sermons, 1322-1380 (Box 20)
  - Sermons, 1381-1432 (Box 21)
  - Sermons, 1433-1488 (Box 22)
  - Sermons, 1489-1545 (Box 23)
  - Sermons, 1546-1593 (Box 24)
  - Sermons, 1594-1651 (Box 25)
  - Sermons, 1652-1713 (Box 26)
  - Sermons, 1714-1779 (Box 27)
  - Sermons, 1780-1844 (Box 28)
  - Sermons, 1845-1898 (Box 29)
  - Sermons, 1899-1958 (Box 30)
  - Sermons, 1959-2015 (Box 31)